# Diyaselis **Delgado**

## Ph.D. Student | Experimental High Energy Physics

diyaselis.github.io in linkedin.com/in/diyaselis

github.com/diyaselis orcid.org/0000-0002-4306-8828

Graduate student and research associate in the Laboratory for Particle Physics and Cosmology (LPPC) at Harvard University, in Professor Carlos Argüelles-Delgado's group. Currently working in the IceCube Neutrino Observatory at the South Pole, with interests in neutrino phenomenology and Dark Matter studies.



## **EDUCATION**

2020 - Present Ph.D. in Experimental High Energy Physics, Harvard University

B.Sc. in Theoretical Physics and Applied Mathematics, University of Puerto Rico - Mayagüez



## PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

## Present September 2020

## Research Assistant | HARVARD UNIVERSITY, MA, USA

> Under supervision of Professor Carlos Argüelles Delgado.

Neutrino Physics Astrophysics HEP - Phenomenology BSM Dark Matter

## August 2019 May 2019

### Research Assistant | CORNELL UNIVERSITY, NY, USA

- > Under the supervision of Professor Jim Alexander, as part of the CLASSE-REU program.
- > Evaluated strain gauge measurements of carbon fiber Dee for the CMS Phase-2 Upgrade of the Tracker Forward Pixel Detector.

HEP - Experimental Detector Physics Hardware

## December 2018 June 2018

## Research Assistant | CERN, Geneva, Switzerland

- > Under the supervision of Dr. Kati Lassila-Perini, as part of the CERN Non-Member State Summer Student program.
- > Working period of September to December was sponsored by the University of Michigan Ann Arbor CERN REU program.
- > Tested various analysis examples for preservation and reproducibility via computational workflows for the CMS experiment.
- > Major contribution to the computational workflows for the analysis with CMS 2011-2012 raw data and Monte Carlo simulations to re-implement the Higgs boson discovery.

HEP - Experimental Open-Data Analysis Software Development

## May 2020 August 2017

### Research Assistant | University of Puerto Rico - Mayagüez, PR, USA

- > Under the supervision of Professor Sudhir Malik.
- > Analyzed event displays for optimized particle identification from proton-proton beam collisions in the CMS Detector, specialized searches for supersymmetry (SUSY) and top tagging.

HEP - Experimental CMS BSM Analysis Software Development Machine Learning



## Awards and Scholarships

2022 Fellowship, European Physical Society Fellowship for the Intl. School of Nuclear Physics, ERICE, ITALY

2022 Scholarship, Jens Aubrey Westengard Scholarship, HARVARD UNIVERSITY, MA, USA

2022 Scholarship, Leon Rosenfeld Foundation, NIELS BOHR INSTITUTE, COPENHAGEN, DENMARK

2022 Grant, International Conference on High Energy Physics (ICHEP), BOLOGNA, ITALY

2020 Fellowship, Harvard Graduate School of Arts and Sciences Prize Fellowship, MA, USA

2020 Award, Enrico Fermi Award, Department of Physics, U. Puerto Rico, Mayagüez, PR, USA

2019 Scholarship, Retired Professor's Association (ACJ) Scholarship, MAYAGÜEZ, PR, USA

2017 Scholarship, Retired Professor's Association (ACJ) Scholarship, MAYAGÜEZ, PR, USA



## COMMUNITY INVOLVEMENT AND OUTREACH

- > IceCube Diversity Taskforce Member, IceCube Collaboration.
- > IAIFI Affiliate Member, NSF AI Institute for Artificial Intelligence and Fundamental Interactions.
- > IceCube Collaboration MasterClass (English & Spanish), Outreach activity for students.
  - Los Amigos Middle School, Cambridge, MA (May 2022)
- > Women in Physics Member, Harvard University Chapter
- > SACNAS Affiliate Member, Society for Advancement of Chicanos/Hispanics & Native Americans in Science.
  - Outreach and Recruitment Involvement for Harvard University.

1



## Present September 2022

## Undergraduate Level Teaching Assistant | HARVARD UNIVERSITY, MA, USA

> I was a teaching assistant of the following Physics classes:

Introductory Electromagnetism and Statistical Physics

May 2020 January 2018

Undergraduate Level Teaching Assistant | University of Puerto Rico - Mayagüez, PR, USA

I was a teaching assistant of the following GENERAL SCIENCE classes:

Calculus General and Advanced Physics Probability and Statistics Computational Techniques in Science and Engineering

## CONFERENCES AND WORKSHOPS

#### INVITED TALKS AND SEMINARS

INTERNATIONAL SCHOOL OF NUCLEAR PHYSICS, ETTORE MAJORANA FOUNDATION, ERICE, ITALY Plenary Talk

SEPTEMBER 2022

DARK GHOSTS, UNIVERSITY OF GRANADA, GRANADA, SPAIN Parallel Talk

MARCH 2022

#### TALKS AND SEMINARS

TEVPA, QUEEN'S UNIVERSITY, KINGSTON, CANADA Parallel Talk

AUGUST 2022

NBIA NEUTRINO SUMMER SCHOOL, NIELS BOHR INSTITUTE, COPENHAGEN, DENMARK Seminar Talk

**JULY 2022** 

APS APRIL MEETING, NEW YORK CITY, NY, USA Parallel Talk

APRII 2022

TEVPA (ONLINE), CHENGDU, CHINA Parallel Talk

DECEMBER 2021

COMHEP (ONLINE), CHENGDU, CHINA Parallel Talk

DECEMBER 2021

CMSDAS, FERMI NATIONAL LABORATORY (FERMILAB), BATAVIA, IL, USA Parallel Talk

JANUARY 2020

PHYSICS SYMPOSIUM, UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO, MAYAGÜEZ, PR, USA Plenary Talk

SEPTEMBER 2019

JTM/PRISM CONFERENCE, UNIVERSITY OF PUERTO RICO, MAYAGÜEZ, PR, USA Parallel Talk

MAY 2019

CERN STUDENT SYMPOSIUM, CERN, GENEVA, SWITZERLAND Parallel Talk

DECEMBER 2018

### **POSTER SESSIONS**

ICHEP, BOLOGNA, ITALY

**JULY 2022** 

NEUTRINO 2022 (ONLINE), SEOUL, SOUTH KOREA

MAY 2022

ASTRODARK (ONLINE), KAVLI IPMU, TOKYO, JAPAN

DECEMBER 2021

SPS PHYSCON, PROVIDENCE, RI, USA

NOVEMBER 2019

APS APRIL MEETING, DENVER, CO, USA

**APRII 2019** 

APS CUWIP MEETING, NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY, EVANSTON, IL, USA

JANUARY 2019

CERN SUMMER STUDENT POSTER SESSION, CERN, GENEVA, SWITZERLAND

AUGUST 2018



## PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

### **SELECTED PUBLICATIONS IN PARTICLE PHYSICS**

SEARCHES FOR CONNECTIONS BETWEEN DARK MATTER AND HIGH-ENERGY NEUTRINOS WITH ICECUBE, PREPRINT ARXIV: 2205.12950. IceCube Collaboration. Submitted to JCAP.

CONTRIBUTION: Reviewed and edited plots and content for final draft submission.

### SELECTED PUBLICATIONS IN ASTROPHYSICS AND ASTROPARTICLE PHYSICS

DARK MATTER DECAY TO NEUTRINOS, PREPRINT ARXIV: 2210.01303. C.A. Argüelles, D. Delgado, A. Friedlander, A Kheirandish, I. Safa, A.C. Vincent, and H. White.

CONTRIBUTION: Computed the galactic contribution from gamma-ray experiments; aided the galactic computation of the neutrino experiments.

## SELECTED PUBLICATIONS IN STATISTICS, COMPUTING, AND EXPERIMENTAL METHODS

OPEN DATA PROVENANCE AND REPRODUCIBILITY: A CASE STUDY FROM PUBLISHING CMS OPEN DATA, EPJ WEB CONF. 245 (2020) 08014. T. Šimko, H. de Bittencourt, E. Carrera, Edgar, D. Delgado, C. Lange, K. Lassila-Perini, A. Lintuluoto, L. Lloret, T. McCauley, J. Okraska, D. Prelipcean, and M. Savaniakas.

CONTRIBUTION: Contributed to the development of the platform and implemented testing examples using CMS Open Data.